I have never, ever forgotten the words of my grandmother
لم أنس أبداً كلمات جدتى
who died in her exile:
التى ماتت فى المنفي
"Son, resist Gaddafi. Fight him.
بني,"قاوم القذافى و حاربه
But don't you ever turn
و لكن لا تتحول أبداً
into a Gaddafi-like revolutionary."
إلى ثائر كالقذافى."
Almost two years have passed
مر قرابة السنتين
since the Libyan Revolution broke out,
على إندلاع الثورة الليبية،
inspired by the waves of mass mobilization
المستوحاة من موجات الحراك الجماهيري
in both the Tunisian and the Egyptian revolutions.
في كل من الثورتين التنوسية و المصرية.
I joined forces with many other Libyans inside and outside Libya
تعاونت مع العديد من الليبين داخل و خارج ليبيا
to call for a day of rage
للدعوة من أجل يوماً للغضب
and to initiate a revolution against the tyrannical regime of Gaddafi.
و لبدء ثورة ضد نظام القذافى الإستبدادى.
And there it was, a great revolution.
و ها هى كانت، ثورة عظيمة.
Young Libyan women and men were at the forefront
كان الشباب و الفتيات الليبيين فى الصدارة
calling for the fall of the regime,
يدعون إلى إسقاط النظام،
raising slogans of freedom, dignity, social justice.
يرفعون شعارات الحرية والكرامة و العدالة الإجتماعية.
They have shown an exemplary bravery
و لقد أظهروا مثالاً يحتذي به للشجاعة
in confronting the brutal dictatorship of Gaddafi.
فى مواجهة دكتاتورية القذافى الوحشية.
They have shown a great sense of solidarity
أظهروا قدراً عظيماً من القدرة على التماسك
from the far east to the far west to the south.
من أقصى الشرق إلى أقصى الغرب إلى الجنوب.
Eventually, after a period of six months of brutal war
أخيراً، و بعد الحرب الوحشية التى إمتدت إلى فترة الستة أشهر
and a toll rate of almost 50,000 dead,
و عدد قتلى يصل إلى قرابة الخمسين ألف قتيلاً،
we managed to liberate our country and to topple the tyrant.
تمكنا من تحرير بلادنا و الإطاحة بالمستبد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
However, Gaddafi left behind a heavy burden,
و لكن، القذافى ترك خلفه حمل ثقيل،
a legacy of tyranny, corruption and seeds of diversions.
ميراث من الإستبداد والفساد و بذور التفرقة.
For four decades Gaddafi's tyrannical regime
لأربعة عقود قام نظام القذافى الاستبدادي
destroyed the infrastructure as well as the culture and the moral fabric of Libyan society.
بتدمير البنية التحتية إلى جانب الثقافة و النسيج الأخلاقى للمجتمع الليبى.
Aware of the devastation and the challenges,
مدركة للخراب و التحديات،
I was keen among many other women to rebuild the Libyan civil society,
بين العديد من النساء الأخريات كنت حريصة على إعادة بناء المجتمع المدنى الليبى،
calling for an inclusive and just transition
داعية إلى الإنتقال الشامل و العادل
to democracy and national reconciliation.
للديمقراطية و المصالحة الوطنية.
Almost 200 organizations were established in Benghazi
تم إنشاء حوالى 200 منظمة فى بنغازى
during and immediately after the fall of Gaddafi --
خلال و مباشرة بعد سقوط القذافى
almost 300 in Tripoli.
ونحو 300 فى طرابلس.
After a period of 33 years in exile, I went back to Libya,
بعد فترة 33 عاماً في المنفي، عدت الي ليبيا
and with unique enthusiasm,
شاعرة بحماس فريد من نوعه،
I started organizing workshops
بدأت بتنظيم ورشات عمل
on capacity building, on human development of leadership skills.
لبناء القدرات، في التنمية البشرية لمهارات القيادة.
With an amazing group of women,
مع مجموعة مذهلة من النساء،
I co-founded the Libyan Women's Platform for Peace,
شاركت فى تأسيس منبر المرأة الليبية من أجل السلام،
a movement of women, leaders, from different walks of life,
حركة نسائية، قادة، من مختلف نواحى الحياة،
to lobby for the sociopolitical empowerment of women
للضغط من أجل تعزيز المرأة في الجانب السياسى الإجتماعى
and to lobby for our right
و للضغط للحصول على حقوقنا
for equal participation in building democracy and peace.
فى المشاركة على قدم المساواة فى بناء الديمقراطية والسلام.
I met a very difficult environment in the pre-elections,
لقد قابلت بيئة صعبة جداً قبل الإنتخابات،
an environment which was increasingly polarized,
بيئة إتسمت بالتفرقة المتزايدة،
an environment which was shaped by the selfish politics of dominance and exclusion.
بيئة تم تشكيلها على يد السياسة الأنانية للهيمنة والإقصاء.
I led an initiative by the Libyan Women's Platform for Peace
قُدت مبادرة لمنبر المرأة الليبية من أجل السلام
to lobby for a more inclusive electoral law,
للضغط من أجل قانون انتخابي أكثر شمولاً
a law that would give every citizen, no matter what your background,
قانون يمنح كل مواطن بغض النظر عن خلفيته،
the right to vote and run,
الحق فى التصويت و الترشح،
and most importantly to stipulate on political parties
والأهم من ذلك الاشتراط على الأحزاب السياسية
the alternation of male and female candidates
اختلاف المرشحين من الذكور و الإناث
vertically and horizontally in their lists,
رأسياً وأفقياً فى قوائمهم،
creating the zipper list.
بانشاء القائمة المترابطة والمتشابكة.
Eventually, our initiative was adopted and successful.
في النهاية، اعتمدت مبادرتنا وتكلل عملنا بالنجاح.
Women won 17.5 percent of the National Congress
فاز النساء بنسبة 17.5 بالمئة من المؤتمر الوطني
in the first elections ever in 52 years.
في اول انتخابات علي الاطلاق خلال 52 عاما.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
However, bit by bit, the euphoria of the elections,
و لكن، شيئا فشيئا، نشوة الانتخابات
and of the revolution as a whole,
والثورة ككل
was fading out --
تلاشت
for every day we were waking up to the news of violence.
كل يوم نفيق علي أخبار العنف
One day we wake up to the news
يوما نفيق علي أخبار
of the desecration of ancient mosques and Sufi tombs.
تدنيس المساجد القديمة والمقابر الصوفية.
On another day we wake up to the news
ويومًا نفيق علي أخبار
of the murder of the American ambassador and the attack on the consulate.
قتل السفير الأمريكي و الإعتداء علي القنصلية الامريكية.
of the assassination of army officers.
وإغتيالات ضباط الجيش.
And every day, every day we wake up with the rule of the militias
وفي كل يوم، كل يوم نستيقظ مع حكم الميليشيات
and their continuous violations of human rights of prisoners
وعلى انتهاكاتiم المستمرة لحقوق الإنسان للسجناء
and their disrespect of the rule of law.
وعدم إحترامهم لسيادة القانون.
Our society, shaped by a revolutionary mindset,
لقد شُكل مجتمعنا بالعقلية الثورية
became more polarized
وأصبح أكثر انقساما
and has driven away from the ideals and the principles --
واقتيد بعيدا عن المبادئ و المثل
freedom, dignity, social justice --
الحرية والكرامة والعدالة الاجتماعية
that we first held.
اللاتي تمسكنا بهم في البداية
Intolerance, exclusion and revenge
التعصب والإقصاء والإنتقام
became the icons of the [aftermath] of the revolution.
أصبحوا رموز ما بعد الثورة
I am here today not at all to inspire you
أنا لست هنا اليوم لإلهامكم
with our success story of the zipper list and the elections.
بقصتنا الناجحة عن القائمة المترابطة والإنتخابات.
I'm rather here today to confess
ولكني هنا لأعترف
that we as a nation took the wrong choice, made the wrong decision.
نحن كأمة اتخذنا خيار خاطئ وصنعنا قرار خاطئ.
We did not prioritize right.
لم نختر الأولويات الصحيحة.
For elections did not bring peace and stability and security in Libya.
hلإنتخابات لم تجلب السلام والإستقرار والأمن في ليبيا.
Did the zipper list and the alternation between female and male candidates
هل حققت القائمة المتداخلة والتناوب بين المترشحين من الرجال و النساء
bring peace and national reconciliation?
السلام والمصالحة الوطنية؟
No, it didn't.
لا، لم تفعل.
What is it, then?
ما هي اذن؟
Why does our society continue to be polarized and dominated
لماذا مجتمعنا لا يزال يهيمنان عليه الإنقسام و السيطرة
with selfish politics of dominance and exclusion, by both men and women?
من سياسيات الأنانية والهيمنة من الرجال والنساء علي حد سواء
Maybe what was missing was not the women only,
ربما ما نفقده هو ليس المرأه فقط،
but the feminine values of compassion, mercy and inclusion.
إنما قيم المرأة من تعاطف ورحمة وتضامن.
Our society needs national dialogue and consensus-building
مجتمعنا في حاجة إلي الحوار الوطني وبناء التوافق
more than it needed the elections,
أكثر من الحاجة للإنتخابات،
which only reinforced polarization and division.
والتي عززت التشتت والإنقسام.
Our society needs the qualitative representation of the feminine
مجتمعنا في حاجة الي التمثيل الكيفي للإنثى
more than it needs the numerical, quantitative representation of the feminine.
أكثر من الحاجة الي التمثيل الرقمي والكمي للإناث.
We need to stop acting as agents of rage and calling for days of rage.
يجب ان نتوقف عن التصرف كوكلاء للغضب والدعوة لأيام من الغضب.
We need to start acting as agents of compassion and mercy.
نحن نحتاج إلي العمل كوكلاء للرحمة والتعاطف.
We need to develop a feminine discourse
نحتاج لتطوير حوار انثوي
that not only honors but also implements
وهذا ليس شرفيًا فحسب و لكن ايضا تنفيذيًا
mercy instead of revenge, collaboration instead of competition,
الرحمة بدلا من الإنتقام والتعاون بدلاً من المنافسة،
inclusion instead of exclusion.
لم الشمل بدلا من الإقصاء.
These are the ideals that a war-torn Libya
هذة هي المثل التي مزقتها الحرب في ليبيا
needs desperately in order to achieve peace.
في حاجة ماسة لتحقيق السلام.
For peace has an alchemy,
السلام لدية تناغم،
and this alchemy is about the intertwining, the alternation
وهذا التناغم عبارة عن تبادل وترابط
between the feminine and masculine perspectives.
بين وجهات النظر للجنسين.
That's the real zipper.
هذا هو الرابط الحقيقي.
And we need to establish that existentially
و نحتاج لبناء هذا الترابط
before we do so sociopolitically.
قبل أن نفعل ذلك اجتماعيًا وسياسيًا.
According to a Quranic verse
وفقا للأيه القرآنية "
"Salam" -- peace -- "is the word of the all-merciful God, raheem."
سلام ’السلام’ هي كلمة الله الرحيم ’رحيم’."
In turn, the word "raheem," which is known in all Abrahamic traditions,
في المقابل، فإن كلمة "الرحيم"، والذي تعرف في جميع التعاليم الإبراهيمية،
has the same root in Arabic as the word "rahem" -- womb --
لها نفس الأصل في اللغة العربية ككلمة "رحم" رحم
symbolizing the maternal feminine encompassing all humanity
ترمز إلي الأمة التي تشمل البشرية جمعاء
from which the male and the female,
التي منه الرجل و المرأة،
from which all tribes, all peoples, have emanated from.
والتي انبثق منها جميع القبائل و جميع الشعوب.
And so just as the womb entirely envelopes the embryo, which grows within it,
ومثلما الرحم يحمي الجنين الذي ينمو في داخلة،
the divine matrix of compassion nourishes the entire existence.
هذة المصفوفة من الرحمة الإلهية تغذي الوجود بأكمله.
Thus we are told that "My mercy encompasses all things."
هكذا قيل لنا أن "رحمتي وسعت كل شيء."
Thus we are told that "My mercy takes precedence over my anger."
وقيل لنا " رحمتي تسبق غضبي".
May we all be granted a grace of mercy.
اللهم أمنحنا جميعا نعمة الرحمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا.